Hey, Haircut. What's up?
Hei, Rambut Gaya. Apa kabar?
It's all good. People seem nice.
Aman. Warganya kelihatannya baik.
What do you want to check?
Apa yang mau kau cek?
We're late.
Kita terlambat.
Yes. I'm sorry.
Ya. Maaf.
I'm sorry too.
Aku juga minta maaf.
Have you settled in here yet?
Sudah betah di sini?
Well, getting there.
Yah, pelan-pelan.
They banished you here, but it's not the end of the world.
Kau dibuang ke sini, tapi di sini tidak buruk-buruk amat, kok.
Lie low for a few years, and they'll forget.
Jangan mencolok dulu beberapa tahun.
You can't punish prosecutors for catching murderers.
Tidak bisa menghukum jaksa karena menangkap pembunuh.
Who knows? You might even like it here.
Siapa tahu kau akan suka di sini.
-Hey.
Hei.
How was your evening?
Bagaimana malammu?
Great. I was exploring the town.
Bagus. Melihat-lihat kota.
-Seriously? -No.
Sungguh?
You should. Trulocz's history dates back to the Neolithic.
Lihat-lihatlah. Sejarah Trulocz dimulai sejak zaman Neolitikum.
What's this?
Apa itu?
Your new case.
Kasus barumu.
-Theft at a liquor store? -The dark side of the town.
Pencurian di toko miras?
Remember a missing boy case from two years ago?
Ingat kasus anak hilang dari dua tahun lalu?
Adam Poznański?
Adam Poznański?
Yes.
Ya…
The mother reported it.
Ibunya yang melaporkan.
Helicopters, dogs,
Helikopter, anjing,
scouring the woods.
penyisiran hutan.
Two days later, she remembered he was with the family.
Dua hari kemudian, dia ingat anaknya bersama keluarganya.
How could she not know that?
Kok dia bisa lupa?
Why do you ask?
Kenapa kau tanya?
My friend has a problem with the statistics.
Kawan di Polda ada masalah dengan statistiknya.
He can't close it. An error pops up.
Kasusnya tak bisa ditutup. Muncul pesan eror.
Typical. You have to go to Chief Adamczyk so they fix it in the system.
Itu biasa. Harus ke Pak Kapolda Adamczyk supaya diperbaiki di sistem.
The boy sang beautifully. I remember from church.
Suara anak itu bagus. Aku ingat di gereja.
You're religious?
Kau religius?
More like superstitious.
Percaya takhayul tepatnya.
And you?
Kau sendiri?
-Ruchanki. -Thanks.
Ruchanki.
-Ruchanki? -Don't ask.
Ruchanki?
-When is your daughter coming? -Tomorrow.
- Kapan putrimu datang? - Besok.
Good. She'll see our Dożynki. There's going to be a big fair.
Bagus.
And you're that crime writer who bought a house by the lake?
Kau penulis kriminal yang beli rumah di tepi danau itu?
-Julia Sarman. Good morning. -Good morning.
Julia Sarman. Selamat pagi.
This is my son, Piotruś.
Ini putraku, Piotruś.
Elżbieta Pakosz. Sorry, it's a small town. Everyone knows everything.
Elżbieta Pakosz. Maaf, ini kota kecil. Semua orang tahu semuanya.
Here you have two of your colleagues.
Ini dua rekanmu.
-Writers? -Almost. Prosecutors.
Penulis?
What a cute boy.
Kau tampan sekali.
Just like my Michaś.
Seperti Michaś-ku.
You have to meet him. He's very shy.
Kalian harus bertemu. Dia sangat pemalu.
-Mom. -What?
- Ibu. - Apa?
I was in labor for 24 hours
Aku melahirkan selama 24 jam
because he was going butt first, and that's how he stayed.
karena pantatnya duluan yang keluar dan posisinya tetap begitu.
Mine was four hours.
Persalinanku empat jam.
He was covered in the sac. I thought he had no face.
Dia terbungkus kantong ketuban. Kukira tidak punya wajah.
So he was born with a caul!
Dia lahir terbungkus ketuban!
And who's going to pay the bill?
Tagihannya siapa yang bayar?
I'll pay in kind.
Kubalas dengan jasa.
My husband.
Suamiku.
Chief.
Pak.
-Good morning. -Good morning, Leopold.
Selamat pagi.
Do you remember a missing boy case from two years ago, Adam Poznański?
Bapak ingat kasus anak hilang dari dua tahun lalu, Adam Poznański?
I do.
Ingat.
My friend from regional police is doing statistics
Teman saya di Polda sedang membuat statistik
and says there's no report in the system.
dan katanya laporannya tidak ada di sistem.
Tell your police friend to check again. Everything's in order on my end.
Suruh teman polisimu lihat lagi. Di tempatku semuanya beres.
We're not in Sopot.
Ini bukan Sopot.
I'll tell him. Thank you.
Akan saya sampaikan. Terima kasih.
-But… the boy was found, right? -Yes.
- Tapi… anak itu sudah ditemukan, ya? - Ya.
With his family?
Dengan keluarganya?
Are you interrogating me, sonny?
Kau menginterogasi aku, Nak?
Just asking.
Bertanya saja.
He was with his family. His mother is an idiot. Literally.
Dia bersama keluarganya. Ibunya keterbelakangan mental. Sungguhan.
I understand. Thank you.
Baiklah. Terima kasih.
You're welcome.
Sama-sama.
Warsaw fuckwit.
Dasar bajingan Warsawa.
Poznański's files are not in the archive.
Berkas Poznański tidak ada di arsip.
-They have to be there. -And if they're not?
Seharusnya ada.
Maybe with the police. Ask Adamczyk.
Mungkin di kepolisian. Tanya Adamczyk.
I asked. He told me to fuck off.
Sudah. Aku malah diusir.
Really?
Sungguh?
Do you know where the boy's parents live?
Kau tahu di mana rumah orang tuanya?
Why? Are you bored?
Kenapa? Kau bosan?
Ewelina looks at him like he's a saint. I know this will only cause trouble.
Ewelina menganggapnya malaikat. Aku tahu ini hanya akan menimbulkan masalah.
You have a nice house.
Rumah kalian bagus.
Thanks. It's not finished yet. We've built it recently.
Terima kasih. Belum selesai. Baru saja kami bangun.
Well, with three kids, it must be hard.
Dengan tiga anak, pasti sulit.
What three kids? I have four to support.
Tiga anak apa? Empat anak yang harus ditanggung.
But it's good that there's the 800 plus.
Tapi untung ada tunjangan 80+.
I hope they don't cancel it. My husband sometimes earns a bit, but…
Semoga tetap jalan. Suami kadang dapat uang sedikit, tapi…
At least the bills pay themselves.
Setidaknya tagihan terbayar.
The bills pay themselves?
Tagihan terbayar?
I didn't mean it like that. What is this about?
Saya salah bicara.
-It's about your son, Adaś. -What about him?
Tentang putra Ibu, Adaś.
Two years ago, you reported him missing, and then withdrew the report.
Dua tahun lalu, Ibu melaporkan dia hilang, lalu membatalkan laporan itu.
So what?
Lantas?
-So your son was found, right? -Yes.
Jadi, putra Ibu sudah ditemukan?
And is he here now?
Dia ada di sini sekarang?
-No, he lives with relatives. -In Trulocz?
Tidak, dia tinggal dengan kerabat.
No, not in Trulocz.
Tidak di Trulocz.
So where?
Lalu di mana?
On the other side of Poland. I lost the address during the move.
Di bagian lain Polandia. Saya lupa di mana menaruh alamatnya.
What are their names?
Siapa nama mereka?
I don't remember.
Saya tidak ingat.
The names of your relatives?
Tidak ingat nama kerabat?
We're not close. My mother's cousin. She wanted to help.
Kami tidak dekat. Dia sepupu ibu saya. Dia ingin membantu.
I'll tell you if I find it.
Kalau ketemu saya beri tahu.
Ewelina is young. Takes everything seriously.
Ewelina masih muda. Semua dianggap serius.
It's kind of funny…
Ini agak lucu…
So you're not in touch with your son?
Jadi, Ibu tidak berhubungan dengan putra Ibu?
With so many kids, you don't have much time.
Kalau punya anak banyak, tidak banyak punya waktu.
Do you have children?
Bapak punya anak?
-I do, yes. -So you know exactly how it is.
Punya.
How did she die, Mom?
Bagaimana meninggalnya, Bu?
Mom?
Ibu?
Mom!
Ibu!
You did it again.
Ibu begitu lagi.
I'm sorry.
Maaf.
Julia?
Julia?
Don't you recognize me? Patryk Deczer. From high school.
Tidak ingat aku? Patryk Deczer. Teman SMA.
Hi.
Hai.
Wow, that's crazy. Damn, why didn't you say you were back?
Wah, gila. Astaga, kenapa tidak bilang sudah kembali?
Guys from school would be happy. Maybe we could have a barbecue?
Teman-teman sekolah pasti senang. Mungkin kita bisa manggang?
How are you doing?
Bagaimana kabarmu?
I don't know if you remember, but I used to paint in high school.
Entah kau ingat atau tidak, tapi aku dulu suka melukis semasa SMA.
And I still do.
Masih sampai sekarang.
I recently had my own exhibition in Copenhagen.
Aku baru-baru ini mengadakan pameran solo di Kopenhagen.
Piotruś.
Piotruś.
Hi, Piotrek.
Hai, Piotrek.
Grandma must be happy to have a grandson.
Neneknya pasti senang punya cucu.
We haven't had time to see her yet.
Kami belum sempat menemuinya.
Listen, maybe get in touch, and we'll organize a meeting with friends.
Berkabar, ya? Kita bisa atur kumpul-kumpul
-Okay. -Okay?
Oke.
We're in a hurry. See you, Patryk.
Kami cepat-cepat. Sampai jumpa, Patryk.
Bye. Bye, Piotrek!
Sampai jumpa. Sampai jumpa, Piotrek!
Why aren't we going to Grandma's?
Kenapa kita tidak ke rumah Nenek?
Because she doesn't want to know me.
Dia tidak mau berurusan dengan Ibu.
What happened back then?
Memangnya ada kejadian apa?
I don't know exactly.
Tidak tahu juga.
But something bad.
Tapi sesuatu yang buruk.
What's on your mind?
Memikirkan apa?
Dad.
Ayah.
Sometimes I don't remember what he looked like.
Kadang-kadang aku lupa wajahnya.
Look. Wave!
Lihat, ombak!
Barrel, barrel!
Tong, tong!
Look at their castles!
Lihat kastel mereka!
Castle, castle!
Kastel, kastel!
-I think the biggest one, right? -Yes!
Ke yang terbesar, ya?
Okay, go ahead.
Nah, sana.
Mr. Prosecutor?
Pak Jaksa?
Hi. Leopold.
Hai. Leopold.
-Julia. -Nice to meet you.
- Julia. - Senang bertemu.
-Is that your little girl? -Monika.
- Itu anakmu? - Monika.
-Gorgeous. -Thanks.
Cantik.
Is she starting school?
Sudah mulai sekolah?
Next year, in Warsaw. She lives there with her mom.
Tahun depan, di Warsawa. Dia tinggal di sana dengan ibunya.
-Have you been in Trulocz long? -No, not long.
Sudah lama di Trulocz?
And do you like it?
Suka di sini?
Well, it's okay.
Yah, lumayan.
Cool. Me neither.
Oke. Aku juga tidak suka.
So why are you here?
Lalu kenapa di sini?
People get tense when they find out you're a prosecutor?
Apa orang jadi tegang saat tahu kau jaksa?
-Yes, they do. -Doesn't it bother you?
Ya, mereka tegang.
-It does. -Why did you become a prosecutor?
- Ya. - Kenapa kau jadi jaksa?
I've been wondering myself.
Aku juga bertanya-tanya.
Why Trulocz?
Kenapa ke Trulocz?
I'm researching for a book.
Mencari materi untuk bukuku.
The dark past of Kashubia, stuff like that.
Masa lalu kelam Kasubia dan yang semacam itu.
-So Monika's on vacation with her dad? -Yes.
Monika liburan dengan ayahnya?
Mom, the shooting range!
Bu, ayo ke lapangan tembak!
Come visit us if you get bored. We have a house by the lake.
Kunjungi kami kalau kalian bosan. Rumah kami di tepi danau.
I'll let her know. Thanks!
Akan kusampaikan. Makasih!
Hold it. Watch now.
Tunggu. Lihat ini.
Special offer today!
Penawaran spesial hari ini!
Just hit the target, kid,
Tembak sasarannya, Nak,
and your pretty mommy will get a teddy bear to cuddle.
dan ibumu yang cantik akan bisa memeluk boneka beruang.
Yup, I heard you were back.
Ya, kudengar kau kembali.
What, you don't recognize me? You don't recognize me?
Kenapa, tidak mengenaliku?
-Wait, is that your kid? -Let's go.
- Tunggu, itu anakmu? - Ayo pergi.
-We'll come back later. -Hey! Kid!
- Nanti kita ke sana lagi. - Hei! Nak!
Look what your mommy did to me!
Lihat perbuatan ibumu kepadaku!
Go on, look!
Coba lihat!
A very warm welcome to you all. There are so many of you here today.
Selamat datang kepada semuanya. Banyak sekali yang hadir.
-But I remember… -You okay?
- Tapi saya ingat… - Tak apa-apa?
…when I started my first term as mayor 20 years ago,
…ketika pertama kali menjabat sebagai wali kota 20 tahun yang lalu.
I got some advice.
Saya diberi nasihat.
"Listen to the people, Fabiola."
"Dengarkan rakyat, Fabiola."
I try to do that every day, and I hope you can see that in my work.
Saya berusaha melakukan itu setiap hari. Semoga itu tecermin dalam pekerjaan saya.
Thank you. Thank you.
Terima kasih.
But really, this city is growing thanks to you.
Tapi kota ini berkembang berkat kalian semua.
Thanks to the residents, the entrepreneurs,
Berkat penduduk, para pengusaha,
thanks to your cooperation.
berkat kerja sama kita.
Give yourselves a round of applause!
Bagus sekali!
"Listen to the people."
"Dengarkan rakyat."
I got that advice from the late father of today's special guest,
Saya diberi nasihat itu dari almarhum ayah tamu istimewa kita,
Mr. Marek Chojnacki!
Pak Marek Chojnacki!
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
A philanthropist, an entrepreneur, and a fan of Trulocz!
Seorang filantropis, pengusaha, dan penggemar Trulocz!
Would you say a few words?
Mohon memberi kata sambutan.
Thank you very much, Madam Mayor. Good morning, ladies and gentlemen.
Terima kasih, Ibu Wali Kota. Selamat pagi, Warga Sekalian.
It's been a year since my father passed away.
Ayah saya berpulang setahun yang lalu.
Piotruś?
Piotruś?
He loved our city…
Dia mencintai kota kita…
Piotr!
Piotr!
The mayor and I…
Saya dan Ibu Wali Kota…
Piotruś!
Piotruś!
…we want to fund scholarships…
…ingin mendanai beasiswa…
Is something wrong?
Ada masalah?
I don't know what happened to the little brat.
Saya tidak tahu apa yang terjadi dengan bocah itu.
Right after bumping into that slut,
Setelah bertemu pelacur itu…
I left the fair and went to Zagłoba for a beer.
saya pergi dari festival ke Zagłoba untuk cari bir.
The bartender will confirm. Then I went home.
Bartendernya bisa konfirmasi. Lalu saya pulang.
"Bumping into that slut"? Guess you don't like her.
"Bertemu pelacur itu"? Sepertinya kau tidak menyukainya.
-Have you seen my face? -Well, it's hard not to notice.
Lihat wajah saya?
That's right.
Benar.
-She did this, with her buddies. -Really? How did that happen?
Ini ulahnya dan teman-temannya.
She attacked me in high school and left me unconscious,
Saya diserang di SMA, dibiarkan pingsan…
face down in a bonfire.
tertelungkup di api unggun.
-High school? She's from here? -You don't know who she is?
SMA?
It's Julia Burchardt. The naughty daughter of our mayor.
Itu Julia Burchardt.
I don't know the details.
Saya tidak tahu persis.
My son was a guard in a resort during the summer.
Putra saya kerja jadi penjaga resor saat musim panas.
That Julia was there.
Julia itu ada di sana.
Apparently, they kissed.
Mereka berciuman. Lalu teman-teman Julia memukulinya,
The boy's life is ruined with that face.
Hidup anak itu hancur gara-gara wajahnya itu.
Maybe he wanted revenge.
Mungkin dia ingin balas dendam?
Arek wouldn't kidnap a kid.
Arek tidak akan menculik anak kecil.
Are you still the organist at the church?
Bapak masih jadi organis di gereja?
I used to be.
Dulu.
I was an organist, and I led the choir.
Dulu saya organis dan memimpin paduan suara.
-How long did you lead the choir? -About 40 years.
Berapa lama memimpin paduan suara?
I stopped a year ago.
Saya berhenti tahun lalu.
It's hard in a wheelchair.
Sulit kerja di kursi roda.
Remember Adaś Poznański? They say he sang there.
Ingat Adaś Poznański? Katanya dia penyanyi di sana.
The one who went missing and was then found?
Yang hilang, lalu ditemukan itu?
Yes.
Ya.
Nice alto.
Suara altonya bagus.
After he was found, did you see him? Did he come to rehearsals?
Setelah ditemukan, pernah bertemu?
I don't remember.
Saya tidak ingat.
Monika!
Monika!
-Daddy! -I'm here!
- Ayah! - Ayah di sini!
We didn't find Piotruś.
Kami tidak menemukan Piotruś.
But maybe he's at home.
Mungkin dia di rumah?
Piotr!
Piotr!
Piotruś!
Piotruś!
They kill children here, get it?
Orang di sini suka membunuh anak kecil.
-Who kills them? -That's how my sister died.
Siapa yang membunuh?
-She got kidnapped? -No.
- Dia diculik? - Tidak.
What children?
Anak-anak apa maksudnya?
Julia.
Julia.
-What happened to your sister? -She killed herself.
Adikmu kenapa?
-When was that? -When I was little.
Kapan itu?
Julia.
Julia…
-Maybe he's at your mother's? -No. She doesn't know I came back.
Mungkin dia di rumah ibumu?
Maybe Piotruś found out somehow? Maybe he wanted to meet his grandma?
Mungkin Piotruś tahu? Mungkin dia ingin bertemu neneknya?
Is he here?
Dia ada di sini?
Piotr?
Piotr?
-Piotruś? -He's not here.
- Piotruś? - Dia tidak di sini.
-What did you do to him? -What did I do?
Ibu apakan dia?
What did you do to him? I just found out I have a grandson!
Kau yang berbuat apa? Ibu baru tahu Ibu punya cucu!
Piotr!
Piotr!
What are you doing?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
Looking for my son.
Mencari putraku.
Some people aren't fit to have children.
Ada orang yang tidak pantas punya anak.
Piotr!
Piotr!
Piotruś?
Piotruś?
Well? He's not there?
Bagaimana? Tidak ada?
No.
Tidak.
-Are you Piotruś's father? -No, I'm just helping.
Anda ayah Piotruś?
Leopold Bilski, prosecutor's office.
Leopold Bilski, dari kejaksaan.
-Good. -We need to stay calm.
- Bagus. - Kita harus tenang.
Give this to her, please.
Tolong beri dia ini.
It'll get her through the night.
Supaya tenang malam ini.
Here you go.
Silakan.
How are you holding up?
Bagaimana keadaanmu?
Sorry.
Maaf.
They wouldn't let me search.
Aku tidak boleh ikut mencari.
Julia, the whole town's looking.
Julia, satu kota mencarinya.
Piotruś is definitely alive.
Piotruś pasti masih hidup.
Do you know something?
Kau tahu sesuatu?
No, I don't.
Tidak.
But I thought maybe I'd set up a Facebook page.
Tapi mungkin aku akan buat laman Facebook.
People do that in cases like this.
Orang biasanya begitu dalam situasi ini.
We need information. Maybe someone saw something.
Kita butuh informasi. Mungkin ada yang melihat sesuatu.
You're a well-known writer. That'll help too.
Kau penulis terkenal. Itu juga akan membantu.
Easy now.
Tenanglah.
I had a crush on you in high school.
Aku menaksirmu semasa SMA.
You were so lost.
Kau sedang kalut sekali.
When I saw you in the store…
Sewaktu melihatmu di toko…
I realized I still feel it.
kusadari rasa itu masih ada.
I love you, Julia.
Aku mencintaimu, Julia.
What the fuck? Are you fucking nuts?
Apa-apaan kau ini?
Get the fuck out of here.
Enyah kau dari sini.
Get the fuck out of here!
Enyah dari sini!
I'll be in touch when I set up the profile.
Nanti kukabari kalau profilnya sudah siap.
PATRYK DECZER CREATED "SPOTTED TRULOCZ"
PATRYK DECZER MEMBUAT SPOTTED TRULOCZ
We found a body in the woods.
Kami menemukan mayat di hutan.
No, I'm sorry. I'm sorry, Julia. It's not your son.
Tidak, maaf. Maaf, Julia. Itu bukan anakmu.
It's not Piotruś.
Itu bukan Piotruś.
It's not your son, do you hear me?
Itu bukan putramu, mengerti?
It's a skeleton of a child Piotruś's age. A skeleton, you understand?
Itu kerangka anak seusia Piotruś. Kerangka, kau mengerti?
It's been in the woods for at least a year.
Itu sudah di hutan setidaknya setahun.
My mother forced me and my sister to sing in the choir.
Ibuku memaksaku dan adikku menyanyi di paduan suara.
At some point, my sister started acting odd.
Suatu ketika, tingkah adikku mulai aneh.
Didn't want to go to rehearsals.
Tidak mau ikut latihan.
Didn't sleep. She was scared.
Tidak tidur. Dia ketakutan.
Then she poisoned herself.
Lalu dia minum racun.
She was 10, I was 12.
Usianya 10 tahun, aku 12 tahun.
Later, in the back room of the choir, I saw a man
Di ruang belakang paduan suara, aku melihat seorang pria…
abusing a boy.
melecehkan anak laki-laki.
What do you mean "abusing"?
Melecehkan bagaimana?
You know.
Ya itu.
Did you tell anyone?
Ada yang kau beri tahu?
My mother, but she didn't believe me. She's too religious.
Ibuku, tapi dia tidak percaya.
Who was that man?
Siapa pria itu?
I don't know.
Aku tidak tahu.
But I recognized the boy.
Tapi aku tahu anak itu.
It was Michał Pakosz, your boss's son.
Michał Pakosz, putra bosmu.
Monika? Are you here?
Monika? Kau di sini?
I came for my daughter.
Aku mencari putriku.
She was just sitting here.
Dia barusan duduk di sini.
-So where is she? -Maybe in the restroom?
Sekarang di mana?
Monika?
Monika?
Monika, are you here?
Monika, kau di sini?
Honey, are you here?
Sayang, kau di sini?
Monika?
Monika?
She's not in the restroom.
Dia tidak ada di toilet.
She was just drawing here.
Dia tadi menggambar di sini.
Maybe she's with your mother?
Mungkin bersama ibumu?
No, my mom went to the wholesaler.
Tidak, ibu saya pergi ke pusat grosir.
Fuck.
Sialan.
Sorry. I only looked away for a moment.
Maaf. Saya lengah sebentar.
Was she drawing alone?
Dia menggambar sendirian?
Where is she?
Di mana dia?
-Where the fuck is she? -I'm sorry. I don't know.
- Di mana dia? - Maaf. Saya tidak tahu.
Monika?
Monika?
Maybe she went there?
Mungkin dia ke sana?
Excuse me. Have you seen a little girl?
Permisi. Ibu melihat gadis kecil?
-A girl? -Five years old, blonde, this tall.
- Gadis kecil? - Lima tahun, pirang, setinggi ini.
I haven't seen her. What was she wearing?
Tidak lihat. Dia pakai baju apa?
Monika!
Monika!
Daddy!
Ayah!
Honey.
Sayang.
You can't do that. Okay?
Jangan begitu. Mengerti?
You can't go off on your own, okay?
Jangan pergi sendirian, mengerti?
-You can't. -Is that your daughter?
- Jangan. - Itu putri Bapak?
Yes.
Ya.
She said her parents were at work.
Katanya orang tuanya sedang bekerja.
-Thank you. -Don't thank me.
Terima kasih.
-Did you hear about that kidnapped boy? -Yes, I did.
Dengar ada anak yang diculik?
Thank you!
Terima kasih!
-You can't… Okay, honey? -Okay.
- Jangan begitu… Ya, Sayang? - Ya.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
Maafkan Ayah.
Hey.
Hei.
No, nothing happened.
Tidak, tidak ada apa-apa.
I'm sorry, you need to take her.
Maaf, kau perlu mengajak dia.
Next time we'll go to the seaside, okay, honey?
Lain kali kita ke pantai, ya, Sayang?
-It's not safe here. -You're a terrible father.
Di sini tidak aman.
Actually, no.
Oh, salah.
You're not terrible.
Bukan buruk.
You'd have to be there first.
Harus ada dulu.
And you're not around.
Kau tidak pernah ada.
You'll drive safely, yes?
Hati-hati di jalan, ya?
-Bye, honey. -Bye.
- Dadah, Sayang. - Dadah.
-Good morning.
- Selamat pagi.
I'm sorry again. You know, I didn't see her leave.
Mohon maaf sekali lagi. Saya tidak melihat dia pergi.
No, it's okay. I shouldn't have left her. I came to pay for my daughter's food.
Tidak apa-apa. Harusnya tidak kutinggal.
No, no need.
Tidak usah.
You sang in the church choir.
Anda menyanyi di paduan suara gereja.
As a young boy. Why do you ask?
Waktu kecil. Kenapa memangnya?
Did anything unpleasant happen to you then?
Pernah mengalami hal yang tak menyenangkan waktu itu?
Unpleasant?
Tak menyenangkan?
Haven't you heard about the molestation in the choir?
Tidak dengar ada pelecehan di paduan suara?
No.
Tidak.
So nothing like that happened to you?
Jadi, Anda tidak mengalami itu?
Nobody… molested you?
Tidak ada yang…
No. Who told you that?
Tidak… Siapa yang bilang begitu?
What years did you sing?
Tahun berapa ikut paduan suara?
Early 2000s.
Awal tahun 2000-an.
Excuse me. I have to get back to work.
Permisi. Saya harus kembali bekerja.
The skeleton was positioned in a bizarre way.
Kerangka itu disusun dengan cara yang aneh.
The head was cut off from the body and placed between the legs.
Kepalanya dipotong dan ditaruh di antara kaki.
Animals?
Ulah binatang?
They'd scatter the remains, not put the head between the legs.
Kalau itu, pasti jadi berceceran, bukan ditaruh di antara kaki.
You're a hunter. You know that.
Kau pemburu. Kau pasti tahu.
They're examining the body.
Mayatnya sedang diperiksa.
Too early to determine the time of death, but
Terlalu dini untuk menentukan waktu kematian, tapi…
the body may belong to Adam Poznański.
mungkin itu mayat Adam Poznański.
But he wasn't even missing.
Tapi dia tidak hilang.
His mom doesn't know where he is.
Ibunya tidak tahu dia di mana.
We need her DNA samples to compare.
Kita perlu sampel DNA-nya untuk dibandingkan.
-Have you talked to her? -Yes.
- Sudah bicara dengannya? - Sudah.
-What the fuck for? -Calm down.
Untuk apa?
To me, it looks like some satanic ritual.
Menurutku, ini seperti ritual setan.
We need to find out if any cult does that.
Kita harus cari tahu apa ada sekte yang melakukannya.
He was in a church choir. It's worth checking out this lead.
Dia ikut paduan suara gereja. Ada baiknya kita periksa petunjuk ini.
He also went to school and to the store. So what?
Dia juga ke sekolah, ke toko. Lalu kenapa?
I've received information that children might've been abused there.
Saya mendapat informasi anak-anak mungkin dilecehkan di sana.
-From who? -Julia Sarman.
Dari siapa?
That crazy woman?
Perempuan gila itu?
She hasn't been here for 20 years, so when was that?
Dia sudah 20 tahun tidak ke sini. Jadi, kapan itu?
When she was a teenager.
Sewaktu dia remaja.
Do you hear him? Andrzej.
Kau dengar dia? Andrzej.
Piotr Sarman could die at any moment, if he's even still alive.
Piotr Sarman bisa mati kapan saja, itu pun kalau dia masih hidup.
-We don't have time. -It's not enough.
Kita tak punya waktu.
We don't have anything else.
Tidak ada petunjuk lain.
Let's not give in to hysteria.
Tapi jangan ikut-ikutan panik.
Father Wojciech is a good man. It's not a witch hunt.
Romo Wojciech orang baik. Ini bukan perburuan penyihir.
Let's do this by the book.
Ikuti prosedur.
Mother's DNA, pathologist, time of death, circumstances,
DNA ibu, ahli patologi, waktu kematian, keadaan,
local sex offenders, psychiatric patients,
pelaku kejahatan seksual setempat, pasien psikiatri,
Satanists. You know the drill.
Pemuja setan. Kau tahu prosedurnya.
Well then…
Baiklah.
All right, plan the investigation.
Baiklah, rencanakan penyelidikannya.
A boy, about ten years old.
Anak laki-laki, sekitar sepuluh tahun.
The cause of death seems to be a skull injury.
Penyebab kematian tampaknya cedera tengkorak.
A blow with a blunt object.
Dipukul benda tumpul.
The head was removed postmortem.
Kepalanya dipotong setelah kematian.
Could animals have done it?
Apa mungkin itu ulah binatang?
They could've moved the head, but I doubt it.
Mereka bisa memindahkan kepala, tapi kurasa tidak.
The marks on the spine indicate that it was cut off with a small saw.
Bekas di tulang belakang menunjukkan bahwa itu dipotong dengan gergaji kecil.
Maybe… maybe a garden saw.
Mungkin… gergaji taman.
Time of death?
Waktu kematian?
Two years ago, by my estimate, but further tests are needed.
Dua tahun lalu, menurutku. Tapi perlu tes lebih lanjut.
Hey.
Hei.
How's it going? How is she?
Apa kabar? Bagaimana kabarnya?
Why?
Kenapa?
Yeah.
Ya.
Fine.
Baiklah.
Fine!
Ya!
Okay, fine. I'll call you later. Yeah.
Ya sudah. Nanti aku menelepon. Ya.
-A łopi. -What "łopi"?
Itu łopi.
A Kashubian vampire.
Vampir Kasubia.
It eats its own intestines,
Dia makan ususnya sendiri,
then attacks people and drinks their blood.
lalu menyerang orang dan meminum darah mereka.
Apparently, before the war, people often dug up graves in the area
Konon, sebelum perang, orang sering menggali kuburan di sini
and cut off heads of the deceased
dan memotong kepala orang mati
-Like in the movies. -That's why you're superstitious.
Seperti di film.
Every Kashubian is.
Orang Kasubia percaya.
A few years ago, someone desecrated a grave in our cemetery.
Beberapa tahun lalu, ada yang menodai makam di kuburan kami.
Old Filipiak, the organist,
Filipiak Tua, organis itu,
father of the burned guy, caught him at night and got beaten up.
ayah pria yang terbakar, memergokinya malam hari dan dipukuli.
What was Old Filipiak doing in the cemetery at night?
Kenapa dia pergi ke kuburan malam-malam?
I don't know. He's a gravedigger.
Entahlah. Dia penggali kubur.
So the organist was also a gravedigger?
Jadi, organis itu juga penggali kubur?
It's Kashubia.
Inilah Kasubia.
Here you go, son.
Ini, Nak.
Eat, honey.
Makanlah, Sayang.
Eat up.
Makanlah.
I saw a dug-up grave.
Saya melihat kuburan yang digali.
A coffin was pulled out.
Peti matinya ditarik keluar.
The head was cut off and placed between the legs.
Kepalanya dipotong, lalu ditaruh di antara kaki.
Like a łopi.
Seperti łopi.
That vampire?
Vampir itu?
It's a local legend, but people believe it.
Itu legenda setempat, tapi orang percaya.
It's not an easy task. The guy was digging for at least an hour.
Melakukan itu tidak mudah. Pria itu menggali setidaknya sejam.
Guy? How do you know it was a guy?
Pria? Tahu dari mana itu pria?
I don't.
Saya tidak tahu.
I didn't see who it was.
Saya tidak lihat orangnya.
He hit me in the back from behind.
Dia datang dari belakang, memukul saya, lalu saya pingsan.
-I woke up in the hospital. -What time was it?
Sadar di rumah sakit.
After midnight, I guess.
Setelah tengah malam.
What were you doing in the cemetery after midnight?
Kenapa di kuburan setelah tengah malam?
Keeping watch.
Menjaga.
Someone was digging earlier but didn't finish.
Sebelumnya ada yang menggali, tapi tidak selesai.
All right.
Baiklah.
Was there anything wrong in your choir?
Di paduan suara Bapak ada masalah?
Wrong?
Masalah?
Anyone bothering the children? Molesting?
Ada yang mengganggu anak-anak? Melecehkan?
-Did you see anything like that? -No. I didn't.
Melihat yang begitu?
All those years, nothing?
Selama bertahun-tahun?
No one reported anything?
Tidak ada laporan seperti itu?
No.
Tidak.
Hey.
Hei.
Beer?
Bir?
Beer.
Bir.
No, wait. They fucking shoved his head into a fryer.
Tidak, tunggu. Kepalanya didorong ke penggorengan.
What's so funny?
Apa yang lucu?
-Let it go. -With a filter.
- Biar. - Yang ada saringannya.
Yes!
Ya!
What?
Apa?
I asked what's so funny.
Aku tadi tanya apa yang lucu.
Nothing. My friend here was telling a joke.
Tidak ada. Temanku ini tadi punya cerita lucu.
Oh yeah? This friend?
Oh, begitu?
What was the joke? Tell me. Let's have a laugh.
Tentang apa? Ceritakan. Ayo tertawakan sama-sama.
-Go away. We don't want trouble. -Shut your trap.
- Pergilah. Kami tidak mau ribut. - Tutup mulutmu.
What was the joke?
Cerita lucu apa itu?
About your burnt pussy.
Tentang vaginamu yang gosong.
You fucking…
Dasar kau…
The fuck is going on?
Apa-apaan ini?
Sit down or get the fuck out of my bar! What the fuck?
Duduk atau enyah dari barku!
Sit down. The beer's on me.
Duduk. Birnya gratis.
DNA TEST RESULTS
HASIL TES DNA
-Hello, ma'am. -Hello.
- Pagi, Bu. - Pagi.
Can we talk inside?
Bisa bicara di dalam?
Yes, come on in.
Ya, silakan masuk.
-Hello.
- Pagi.
In the course of the investigation,
Dalam proses penyelidikan,
we have determined that the DNA samples from the body are a match with yours.
kami telah memastikan bahwa sampel DNA dari jasad di hutan dan dari Ibu cocok.
This means that the body from the forest belongs to your son, Adam Poznański.
Artinya jasad yang ditemukan di hutan
But my son Adam is with his family.
Tapi anak saya, Adam, bersama keluarganya.
He is not.
Tidak.
Your son Adam is dead.
Adam, anak Ibu, sudah meninggal.
With what family?
Keluarga apa maksudnya?
His adoptive family.
Keluarga angkatnya.
And where do they live?
Di mana tinggalnya?
In Belgium. In Belgium, right?
Di Belgia.
No. The remains of your son Adam were found in the woods. He is dead.
Tidak. Jasad putra Ibu, Adam, ditemukan di hutan. Dia sudah meninggal.
But you said Adam was with his adoptive family in Belgium.
Tapi kata Bapak, Adam bersama keluarga angkatnya di Belgia.
I didn't say that. I just asked you, when he went missing,
Saya tidak bilang begitu. Saya hanya bertanya, saat dia hilang,
if you gave him up.
apa Ibu serahkan untuk diadopsi.
You said they were good people and he'd be better off.
Bapak bilang mereka orang baik dan dia akan lebih baik dengan mereka.
I asked if you sold him for adoption.
Saya bertanya apa Ibu menjualnya untuk diadopsi.
No! You said they were rich and that he was doing well.
Tidak! Bapak bilang mereka kaya dan hidup Adam baik di sana.
I warn you that giving false testimony is punishable by imprisonment.
Awas, memberi kesaksian palsu bisa dihukum penjara.
-Your kids will go to an orphanage. -Did he say he got adopted?
- Anak-anak bisa dibawa ke panti asuhan. - Beliau mengatakan dia diadopsi?
What are you doing?
Apa yang kau lakukan?
Did the chief tell you that Adam was adopted after he went missing?
Apa Pak Kapolda mengatakan Adam diadopsi setelah dia hilang?
I can't believe this.
Yang benar saja, Bilski.
Did the chief tell you that your son was adopted?
Apakah Pak Kapolda mengatakan anak Ibu diadopsi?
No.
Tidak.
He didn't say that?
Beliau tak berkata begitu?
The chief intimidated the witness.
Pak Kapolda mengintimidasi saksi.
I only mentioned criminal liability for giving false testimony.
Aku hanya menyebutkan soal tanggung jawab pidana
Standard procedure.
Prosedur standar.
No, witness intimidation.
Tidak, mengintimidasi saksi.
Andrzej, get this kid off my back.
Andrzej, enyahkan anak ini dariku.
Tell me exactly what you told her after he went missing.
Apa yang persisnya kau katakan kepada ibunya setelah anaknya hilang?
I was egging her on. They're degenerates. They could have sold the kid to someone.
Dia kupancing. Mereka bejat.
Why did she withdraw the report after two days?
Kenapa dia menarik laporan setelah dua hari?
It sounds convincing to me. Doesn't it to you?
Bagiku, itu kurang meyakinkan. Kau sependapat?
To me, it sounds like witness intimidation.
Bagi saya, itu seperti mengintimidasi saksi.
That's a serious accusation.
Itu tuduhan serius.
I've seen many interrogations, but none like that.
Saya sering melihat interogasi, tapi tidak ada yang seperti itu.
You think that because the mafia offed your dad, you can talk like that?
Kau kira karena ayahmu ditembak mafia, kau bisa bicara begitu?
-Pull the stick out of your ass! -Let's end this discussion.
Jangan sok suci!
We have a terrified mother,
Ada ibu yang ketakutan,
a boy who is missing, possibly dead.
seorang anak hilang, kemungkinan mati.
Anything goes. We have to find him.
Apa pun boleh dilakukan. Dia harus ditemukan.
We're still combing the woods. What about the sex offenders?
Kita masih menyisir hutan.
A few guys with rape convictions,
Ada beberapa orang yang dihukum atas pemerkosaan,
but regular ones, no child victims.
tapi yang biasa. Tidak ada korban anak kecil.
-All have alibis. -Check them again.
Semua punya alibi.
-Let's check the church choir lead. -That's hardly a lead.
Kita periksa pemimpin paduan suara gereja.
Yes, but we don't have time.
Ya, tapi tidak ada waktu.
Every hour makes it more likely that he's dead.
Makin lama, kemungkinan dia sudah meninggal makin besar.
You really think he's still alive?
Kau sungguh mengira dia masih hidup?
Listen, we don't have any evidence to stir this kind of shit.
Kita tidak punya bukti, tidak mampu terlibat masalah macam ini.
You're not allowed near the church.
Jangan dekat-dekat gereja.
Hi, Haircut.
Hai, Rambut Gaya.
Now you have to check a few things for me.
Bantu aku memeriksa beberapa hal.
Father Wojciech?
Romo Wojciech?
Praise the Lord. Yes.
Puji Tuhan. Ya.
Leopold Bilski, prosecutor's office. Can we talk?
Saya Leopold Bilski dari kejaksaan. Bisa kita bicara?
Sure, go ahead.
Tentu, silakan.
Did you know Adam Poznański? The one they found in the woods?
Apa Bapak mengenal Adam Poznański? Yang ditemukan di hutan itu?
I'll tell you one thing. I'm an old man.
Saya beri tahu satu hal. Saya ini orang tua.
I remember things from 20, even 40 years ago, but
Saya ingat hal-hal dari 20, bahkan 40 tahun lalu, tapi…
I don't remember what happened yesterday.
saya tidak ingat apa yang terjadi kemarin.
Do you remember Julia Burchardt, sir? Her son went missing.
Bapak ingat Julia Burchardt?
Please call me "Father," okay?
Tolong panggil saya "Romo", ya?
I'm not here as a believer. Remember him, sir?
Saya bukan umat. Ingat dia, Pak?
Oh, right. Burchardt?
Oh, ya. Burchardt?
I remember her poor sister. Yes…
Saya ingat adiknya yang malang itu. Ya…
What about her?
Ada apa?
Julia said she witnessed a boy being molested on church grounds
Julia mengatakan dia menyaksikan ada anak laki-laki dilecehkan di gereja
when she was a choir girl.
saat dia masih di paduan suara.
Such things didn't happen in our parish.
Tidak ada hal seperti itu di paroki kami.
I heard that there were priests in Poland who weren't called to serve,
Saya dengar di suatu tempat di Polandia
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Praise be to Jesus Christ.
Terpujilah Yesus Kristus.
Goodbye.
Sampai jumpa.
Do you remember anything else?
Ada ingat yang lain?
Try to remember that man. Was he tall, short, slim?
Coba ingat pria itu. Apa dia tinggi, pendek, kurus?
I don't know.
Entahlah.
How old was he?
Berapa usianya?
Was he wearing a cassock?
Apa dia pakai jubah?
No, I don't think so.
Rasanya tidak.
Maybe the organist?
Mungkin organis itu?
I don't know. No… I don't think so.
Aku tidak tahu. Bukan… Kurasa bukan.
You know,
Begini…
I got a disciplinary transfer to Trulocz after my previous case.
aku dipindahtugaskan ke Trulocz sebagai sanksi kasus sebelumnya.
The policeman who helped me was banished to desk duty.
Polisi yang membantuku ditugaskan di belakang meja.
He likes statistics. Boring stuff.
Dia suka statistik. Hal yang membosankan.
But he found one strange thing.
Tapi dia menemukan satu hal aneh.
That all over Poland, there are crimes involving minors.
Di seluruh Polandia, ada kejahatan terkait anak di bawah umur.
Sexual, abductions, disappearances, everywhere.
Kejahatan seksual, penculikan, anak hilang. Di mana-mana.
But not here.
Tapi di sini tidak ada.
Nothing in almost 20 years.
Selama hampir 20 tahun tidak ada.
He only found the disappearance of Adam Poznański here.
Yang dia temukan di sini hanya hilangnya Adam Poznański.
It was in some Internet article. There's nothing in the police records.
Itu ada di artikel di internet.
Someone…
Ada yang…
Someone is protecting someone.
melindungi seseorang.
Exactly.
Benar.
Can I hug you?
Boleh aku memelukmu?
I'm sorry.
Maaf.
Oh, I see you went for linen.
Wah, kini rekan kerjaku suka linen.
-Hi, Haircut. -Hey.
- Hai, Rambut Gaya. - Hei.
-Here you go. -Thanks.
- Ini. - Terima kasih.
Fucked-up case.
Kasusnya rusuh.
I checked the Poznańskis' bills with the power and water companies,
Saya memeriksa tagihan listrik dan air keluarga Poznański.
then I checked the construction company that built their house,
Lalu memeriksa perusahaan konstruksi yang membangun rumah mereka.
then I checked the water and power bills for the local presbytery.
Kemudian memeriksa tagihan air dan listrik untuk pastoran setempat.
You know what I found out?
Tahu apa yang saya temukan?
I'm sure you'll tell me.
Pasti Anda akan beri tahu saya.
The bills for both places
Tagihan di kedua tempat itu
are paid by a church foundation set up by Chojnacki.
dibayar oleh yayasan gereja yang didirikan Chojnacki.
The local meat baron.
Raja… daging setempat.
I know who he is.
Saya tahu dia siapa.
We need to raid him.
Dia perlu digerebek.
Adam Poznański went missing. We found him dead in the woods.
Adam Poznański hilang. Kita temukan tewas di hutan.
His mother reported him missing, then withdrew the report.
Ibunya melaporkan dia hilang, lalu menarik laporannya.
She can't say where her son is.
Dia tidak tahu anaknya di mana.
After Adam went missing,
Setelah Adam hilang,
Chojnacki bought her a house and now pays her bills.
Chojnacki membelikannya rumah dan membayar tagihannya.
Now Piotr Sarman is missing,
Sekarang Piotr Sarman hilang
and Julia Sarman claims that, as a child, she saw a boy being molested in the choir.
dan Julia Sarman mengaku melihat anak laki-laki dilecehkan di paduan suara.
And who sponsors the choir?
Sponsor paduan suara itu
Chojnacki's church foundation.
ternyata yayasan gereja Chojnacki.
Which boy?
Anak yang mana?
You mean Sarman's son?
Maksud Bapak anak Sarman?
No. You said that Julia Sarman witnessed a boy being molested.
Tidak. Kau bilang Julia Sarman menyaksikan
So I'm asking, what was the boy's name?
Jadi, aku tanya, siapa nama anak itu?
She claims it was your son, Michał.
Katanya itu putra Bapak, Michał.
Marek Chojnacki?
Marek Chojnacki?
-What is this about? -We have a search warrant.
- Ada apa ini? - Kami membawa surat penggeledahan.
Please wait. I'll call your superior.
Mohon menunggu. Saya akan menelepon atasan Bapak.
-Where is the basement? -Here!
Di mana basemennya?
I want every computer, hard drive, memory card,
Aku mau semua komputer, diska keras, kartu memori,
film, cassette, vinyl, fucking everything.
film, kaset, piringan hitam, semuanya.
FORENSIC TECHNICIAN
TEKNISI FORENSIK
What does the guy do?
Apa pekerjaan orang ini?
Pigs for generations.
Babi turun-temurun.
I'm so jealous!
Aku iri sekali!
Give me a flashlight.
Minta senter.
Piotruś!
Piotruś!
Quiet!
Diam!
Okay, open it.
Buka pintunya.
Get the crowbar!
Ambil linggis!
Piotruś!
Piotruś!
Fucking hell!
Sialan!
Piotruś?
Piotruś?
I found something!
Aku menemukan sesuatu!
Why did you finance Irena Poznańska's house and pay her bills?
KEJARI TRULÔCZ
One of the goals of my father's foundation
Salah satu tujuan yayasan ayah saya
is supporting poor residents of our region.
adalah membantu warga kurang mampu di wilayah kami.
I think it's quite natural that we help Mrs. Poznańska.
Saya rasa wajar saja jika kami membantu Bu Poznańska.
How many other families got a house from you?
Berapa banyak keluarga lain yang Anda beri rumah?
I don't know the exact number. I don't supervise it personally.
Saya tidak tahu jumlah pastinya. Itu tidak saya awasi langsung.
Is the foundation's care for the Poznańskis
Apakah kepedulian yayasan terhadap keluarga Poznański
the only evidence linking my client to a murder case?
satu-satunya bukti yang mengaitkan klienku dengan kasus ini?
Did you know Adam Poznański?
Anda kenal Adam Poznański?
No, I didn't.
Tidak kenal.
This pedophilic photo depicts Adam Poznański.
Di foto bermuatan pedofilia ini ada Adam Poznański.
It was found in your home during the search, along with many others.
Ditemukan saat penggeledahan di rumah Anda beserta banyak yang lainnya.
Did you take this photo?
Anda yang memotret?
-No. -No?
- Tidak. - Tidak?
So who did?
Lalu siapa?
-I don't know. -You don't know?
Saya tidak tahu.
In that case, you will be detained for three months, for now.
Jika demikian, Anda akan ditahan selama tiga bulan. Untuk saat ini.
I'm not sure who took it.
Saya tidak tahu siapa yang memotret.
I think it was my father.
Saya rasa ayah saya.
It's your son.
Itu putra Bapak.
Well. We need to identify the victims, question them, and…
Kita harus mengidentifikasi korban, menanyai mereka, dan…
try to determine the perpetrator.
mencoba mengetahui pelakunya.
The photos were taken over several decades,
Foto-foto itu diambil selama beberapa dekade.
most likely by old Chojnacki.
Kemungkinan besar oleh Chojnacki tua.
His son claims he had that inclination.
Kata putranya, dia memiliki kecenderungan itu.
-Old Chojnacki is dead. -He couldn't have kidnapped Piotr.
Chojnacki tua sudah mati.
What, the young Chojnacki?
Apa, Chojnacki muda?
Maybe, but we searched the house, the meat plants, the estates.
Mungkin, tapi kami menggeledah rumah, pabrik daging, dan tanahnya.
No boy.
Tidak ada anak.
So it's not him.
Jadi, bukan dia.
I don't think so.
Saya rasa bukan.
What do you want to do?
Apa rencanamu?
Like you said, identify and talk to the victims.
Seperti kata Bapak, mengidentifikasi dan bicara dengan korban.
Maybe someone was helping the old man, kidnapped the boy.
Mungkin ada yang membantu ayahnya menculik anak itu.
-And we need to talk to the profiler. -Okay.
Juga perlu ke penyusun profil kriminal.
One more thing.
Satu lagi.
Chief Adamczyk. I think he was covering for the Chojnackis.
Pak Adamczyk.
He's his cousin.
Dia sepupunya.
I'll remove the chief.
Dia akan kucopot.
Do you recognize the victim?
Bapak mengenali korbannya?
Angelika Burchardt.
Angelika Burchardt.
And who is this?
Lalu ini siapa?
Patryk Deczer.
Patryk Deczer.
This one?
Foto ini?
Arek Filipiak.
Arek Filipiak.
Do you recognize this boy?
Bapak mengenali anak laki-laki ini?
Who is this?
Siapa ini?
Michał Pakosz.
Michał Pakosz.
And her?
Gadis ini?
Who is she?
Siapa dia?
I don't want to look. Take this away!
Saya tidak mau melihatnya. Singkirkan!
You have to identify the girl in the photo.
Ibu harus mengidentifikasi gadis di foto itu.
One of the witnesses identified her as your daughter.
Salah satu saksi mengatakan dia adalah putri Ibu.
Angelika?
Angelika?
No, that's not Angelika.
Tidak, itu bukan Angelika.
The victim in the photo is very young,
Korban di foto itu sangat muda.
and only you can confirm her identity.
Hanya Ibu yang bisa mengonfirmasi identitasnya.
I'm sorry, we have to. It's an investigation.
Maaf, kami harus melakukannya. Ini penyelidikan.
First, your mother said it was impossible,
Awalnya, kata ibumu tidak mungkin,
that Chojnacki had no contact with you at that age.
Chojnacki tidak pernah bersamamu waktu kau seusia itu.
Then she remembered the pilgrimage.
Lalu dia ingat ziarah itu.
She let Chojnacki give you a ride to the hotel.
Dia membiarkan Chojnacki mengantarmu ke hotel.
She says it was the only time.
Katanya sekali itu saja.
I don't remember anything.
Aku tidak ingat apa-apa.
I don't want to look.
Aku tidak mau lihat.
In high school, I was in a kind of catatonia.
Waktu SMA, aku mengalami semacam katatonia.
Paralysis.
Lumpuh.
Arek tried getting in my pants, and I couldn't move.
Arek mencoba membuka celanaku dan aku tidak bisa bergerak.
As if I wasn't there inside.
Seperti tubuh tanpa jiwa.
It happened to me many times later in life.
Itu kualami berkali-kali di kemudian hari.
Always during sex.
Selalu saat berhubungan seks.
But I have to ask you to help me identify another girl.
Tapi aku harus memintamu membantu mengidentifikasi gadis lain.
No one remembers her.
Tidak ada yang mengingatnya.
-Do you know her? -I don't.
- Kau kenal dia? - Tidak.
-Are you sure?
- Kau yakin?
It's your mother.
Ibumu datang.
Where's Piotruś?
Di mana Piotruś?
We'll find him.
Akan kita temukan.
I'll have to question you officially.
Aku harus menanyaimu secara resmi.
Fuck me!
Ya ampun!
The Guardian Angel choir!
Paduan suara Malaikat Pelindung!
You too?
Kau juga?
Fuck off.
Berengsek.
Fuck.
Sialan.
I don't know how to do it.
Aku tidak tahu mesti bagaimana.
Together or separately?
Sama-sama atau sendiri-sendiri?
Separately.
Sendiri-sendiri.
Okay, I want to go first.
Baik, aku mau duluan.
Old Chojnacki had the whole town in his pocket.
Chojnacki tua menguasai kota ini.
He gave money to the church, paid for renovations, hired people.
Dia memberi uang ke gereja. Membiayai renovasi. Mempekerjakan orang.
My father got his salary from that old perv.
Ayah saya digaji oleh orang tua mesum itu.
Did you tell anyone what Chojnacki was doing?
Ada yang Anda beri tahu tentang perbuatan Chojnacki?
No, no one. Never.
Tidak ada. Tidak pernah.
Did he do it alone, or did someone help him?
Dia lakukan sendirian? Atau ada yang membantu?
No, no one helped him.
Tidak, tidak ada… yang membantu.
When did it stop?
Kapan berhentinya?
When I said that if he unzipped his fly one more time, I'd bite his dick off.
Waktu saya bilang, kalau dia membuka ritsletingnya lagi, saya gigit kontolnya.
It worked.
Itu mempan.
I don't know.
Aku tidak tahu.
I don't know if he did it alone or someone aided him.
Apa dia lakukan sendirian atau dibantu orang.
I don't remember anything. How old could I have been?
Aku tidak ingat apa-apa. Berapa umurku waktu itu?
Four?
Empat tahun?
Did you tell anyone about what Chojnacki did to you?
Pernah cerita ke orang lain tentang perbuatan Chojnacki?
No.
Tidak.
Why not?
Kenapa?
I don't know.
Entahlah.
I was ten years old.
Usia saya sepuluh tahun.
My mother raised me alone. She worked for Chojnacki, and…
Dibesarkan Ibu sendirian. Dia bekerja untuk Chojnacki. Dan…
Maybe I feared it would hurt her.
Mungkin takut dia kena akibatnya.
It's important. Think.
Ini penting. Pikirkan.
This person could have kidnapped Piotr Sarman.
Orang ini bisa saja menculik Piotr Sarman.
Was someone taking or sending you to him?
Apa ada yang membawa atau mengirim Anda ke dia?
When it happened for the first time, the organist sent me to the back room
Pertama kali terjadi, organis itu menyuruh saya ke ruang belakang
to stamp holy pictures.
untuk mengecap gambar orang suci.
Really? So he knew?
Oh, jadi dia tahu?
He might not have known.
Mungkin tidak tahu.
He's a very religious man.
Orangnya sangat religius.
When did it end?
Kapan itu berakhir?
When I told my mom.
Saat Ibu saya beri tahu.
She forbade me from telling Dad, and
Saya dilarang memberi tahu Ayah dan…
I think she dealt with Chojnacki because it stopped.
Saya rasa dia urus dengan Chojnacki karena tak terjadi lagi.
Then she opened the restaurant.
Setelah itu dia membuka restorannya.
Now what?
Sekarang bagaimana?
If the desecration of the corpse at the cemetery,
Kalau penodaan mayat di kuburan,
the murder of Poznański, and the kidnapping of that last boy
pembunuhan Poznański, dan penculikan anak terakhir ini
are the work of one person,
dikerjakan oleh satu orang, maka kita menghadapi pembunuh berantai
in the early stages of his activity.
di tahap awal aktivitasnya.
First he fantasized,
Pertama, dia berfantasi,
then he played in the cemetery.
lalu dia bermain-main di kuburan,
Finally, he killed.
dan terakhir membunuh.
But that's only if it's the same person.
Tapi itu hanya kalau orangnya sama.
Paranoid schizophrenia develops slowly.
Skizofrenia paranoid berkembang perlahan.
A person fights it,
Dia berusaha melawannya,
but has hallucinations, hears voices, has strong emotions.
tapi mengalami halusinasi, mendengar suara,
There is also a main theme.
Ada juga tema utamanya.
It could be that łopi you mentioned but not necessarily.
Bisa jadi łopi yang Anda sebutkan, tapi belum tentu.
It could be an image from childhood, a story,
Bisa jadi bayangan dari masa kecil, sebuah cerita,
a fight to the death with delusional forces that threaten the sick person.
berjuang mati-matian melawan kekuatan delusi
Damn it.
Sialan.
-Here you go. -Thank you.
- Ini. - Terima kasih.
So we're looking for a person who exhibits noticeable mental aberrations?
Jadi, kita mencari orang yang jelas memperlihatkan gangguan mental?
Yes and no.
Ya dan tidak.
It could be, for example, a paragnomen,
Itu bisa jadi, misalnya, paragnomen,
which is a surprising, unexpected behavior of a healthy person,
yakni tindakan seseorang yang sehat yang mengejutkan, di luar dugaan,
which also often indicates the early stages of the condition.
yang juga sering merupakan stadium awal penyakit ini.
But if it is as I say,
Tapi jika seperti yang saya katakan…
it narrows it down, as the perpetrator is relatively young.
itu mempersempit karena pelakunya relatif muda.
30, 40 years old, no more.
Usia 30, 40 tahun, tidak lebih.
-And can psychosis be caused by trauma? -Yes.
Dan psikosis bisa disebabkan oleh trauma?
Molestation, experience of violence, tragic accidents,
Pelecehan, pengalaman kekerasan, kecelakaan tragis,
but you have to have a predisposition.
tapi harus ada kecenderungan sebelumnya.
If it's a psychopath, he's from here.
Kalau dia psikopat, dia orang sini.
He operates in an environment which is safe for him.
Dia beroperasi di lingkungan yang aman untuk dirinya.
If the legend of the łopi makes sense,
Kalau legenda łopi itu masuk akal,
he is from Kashubia.
dia dari Kasubia.
If he is holding the boy, it is in his home
Jika dia membawa anak itu, pasti di rumahnya
or in a place that belongs to him,
atau di tempat miliknya.
so in Trulocz or the surrounding area.
Jadi, di Trulocz atau sekitarnya.
And does he think he is a łopi, or is he hunting one?
Apa dia berpikir dia itu łopi atau dia memburu łopi?
It's really hard to say.
Itu sulit dipastikan.
There is no logic here. It's a disease. Disturbed emotions.
Ini tidak ada logikanya. Ini penyakit. Emosi yang terganggu.
He cut off the victim's head to stop it,
Dia memotong kepala korban untuk menghentikannya
or he was afraid to cut off his own head.
atau dia takut memotong kepalanya sendiri.
Could it be one of Chojnacki's victims?
Apa mungkin itu salah satu korban Chojnacki?
Maybe, but it doesn't have to be.
Mungkin, tapi belum tentu.
-Maybe someone who helped him? -Maybe.
Mungkin ada yang membantu?
But he would have to have some kind of trauma too.
Tapi dia juga harus punya semacam trauma.
Is Piotr Sarman still alive?
Apa Piotr Sarman masih hidup?
I don't think so.
Saya rasa tidak.
Please.
Kumohon.
And now, everyone.
Sekarang sama-sama.
Haircut, take the boys. Go search Michał Pakosz's house.
Rambut Gaya, bawa anak buahmu. Geledah rumah Michał Pakosz.
Don't tell the old man.
Jangan beri tahu ayahnya.
Piotruś?
Piotruś?
Piotr!
Piotr!
Piotr, are you there?
Piotr, kau di dalam?
Piotruś is not here.
Piotruś tidak ada di sana.
If I were Pakosz, I'd fucking sack you.
Kalau aku Pakosz, kau pasti kupecat.
I'd fucking sack myself.
Aku akan pecat diriku sendiri.
How old are you, Jerzyna?
Berapa umurmu, Jerzyna?
Almost 30.
Hampir 30 tahun.
Around 30, you believe in łopi, you're from here.
Sekitar 30 tahun, kau percaya pada łopi, kau dari sini.
Early stages of psychosis.
Stadium awal psikosis.
You fit the profile.
Kau cocok dengan profilnya.
That's me.
Itu benar aku.
Are you fucking nuts, Bilski?
Kau sudah gila, Bilski?
I jumped to conclusions after talking to the profiler.
Saya langsung menyimpulkan setelah bicara dengan penyusun profil.
What did he say?
Apa katanya?
Male, local, 30, 40 years old,
Pria, orang setempat. Usia 30-40 tahun.
experienced trauma, maybe one of our victims, psychosis.
Mengalami trauma. Mungkin salah satu korban kita. Psikosis.
What now?
Sekarang apa?
We need to identify the girl from the photo
Perlu mengidentifikasi gadis di foto
and go through Chojnacki's foundation's records.
dan memeriksa catatan yayasan Chojnacki.
Here, against the wall.
Di sini, di dinding.
Get in.
Masuk.
No. Here.
Bukan. Di sini.
-Where are you going? -To the organist.
- Mau ke mana? - Ke si organis.
Help me.
Tolong Ayah.
Why didn't you do anything?
Kenapa Ayah tidak berbuat apa-apa?
When?
Kapan?
When he was doing it.
Waktu dia melakukannya.
Why didn't you say anything?
Kenapa kau tidak bilang apa-apa?
Because I was a child.
Karena aku masih kecil.
He never gave anything away.
Dia tidak pernah mencurigakan.
Sometimes he hugged a child, stroked them a little.
Kadang-kadang memeluk dan membelai anak kecil.
You didn't suspect a thing?
Ayah tidak curiga?
He helped us a lot.
Dia banyak membantu kita.
If it wasn't for him…
Kalau bukan karena dia…
you wouldn't have been able to go out.
kau tidak akan bisa keluar rumah.
Remember how it was back then?
Ingat bagaimana dulu?
He paid for transplants, physical therapy.
Dia membiayai transplantasi.
So you knew.
Jadi, Ayah tahu.
Arek!
Arek!
Arek.
Arek…
-Is your father home? -In the bathroom.
- Ayahmu di rumah? - Di kamar mandi.
Hey!
Hei!
Help him.
Tolong dia.
Mr. Filipiak?
Pak Filipiak?
Hello? Are you in there?
Halo? Bapak di dalam?
I remember her being there.
Dia dulu sering ke sana.
But I don't remember her name.
Tapi saya lupa namanya.
Kasia, I think.
Kasia, rasanya.
Or Basia.
Atau Basia.
So, Kasia or Basia?
Kasia atau Basia?
-I don't remember her last name. -Okay, think.
Lupa nama belakangnya.
It's very important.
Ini sangat penting.
I remember her mother used to bring her.
Saya ingat dia suka diantar ibunya.
-And her name? What did she look like? -Her name…
Namanya? Seperti apa dia? Berapa umurnya?
A worn-out woman,
Perempuan yang kacau,
around 30 years old.
usianya sekitar 30 tahun.
Petite.
Mungil.
Worked at a slaughterhouse.
Bekerja di rumah jagal.
For Chojnacki?
Karyawan Chojnacki?
All the slaughterhouses are Chojnacki's.
Semua rumah jagal milik Chojnacki.
Okay. Anything else?
Baiklah. Apa lagi?
You know… I…
Saya…
really liked that job.
sangat suka pekerjaan itu.
I worked with kids.
Saya bekerja dengan anak-anak.
I took care of them.
Saya menjaga mereka.
And? Do you have anything new?
Ada perkembangan baru?
We need to check personnel files for Chojnackis' slaughterhouses.
Kita perlu periksa berkas pegawai di rumah jagal Chojnacki.
We're looking for a petite woman who was in her thirties in the early 2000s
Cari wanita mungil berusia 30-an pada awal tahun 2000-an
and had a daughter named Kasia… or Basia.
dan punya putri bernama Kasia. Atau Basia.
That's fucking great.
Bagus sekali.
Call in reinforcements.
Panggil pasukan.
How's it going?
Ada perkembangan?
It's not. There's too much to do it ourselves.
Tidak. Terlalu banyak hal dan tak bisa kita kerjakan sendiri.
Tell me about that łopi.
Ceritakan tentang łopi itu.
Don't you have Internet on your phone?
Tidak punya internet di ponsel?
I like your voice.
Aku suka suaramu.
What do you need?
Mau tahu tentang apa?
How would someone become a łopi? Does another łopi have to bite you?
Bagaimana orang bisa jadi łopi? Apa harus digigit łopi lain?
No.
Tidak.
When a child was born in an amniotic sac, it was a bad sign.
Saat anak lahir masih terbungkus selaput ketuban, itu pertanda buruk.
They would dry the sac, grind it,
Selaput itu akan dikeringkan, digiling,
and give it to the child with the mother's milk.
lalu diberi ke anak itu dengan ASI ibunya.
Otherwise it would become a łopi, and then…
Kalau tidak, dia akan jadi łopi, lalu…
a shovel and head between the legs.
sekop dan kepala di antara kaki.
I was in labor for 24 hours
Aku melahirkan selama 24 jam
because he was going butt first, and that's how he stayed.
karena pantatnya duluan yang keluar dan posisinya tetap begitu.
Mine was four hours.
Persalinanku empat jam.
He was covered in the sac. I thought he had no face.
Dia terbungkus kantong ketuban. Kukira tidak punya wajah.
So he was born with a caul!
Jadi, dia lahir terbungkus ketuban!
-He was in the restaurant. -Who?
Dia ada di restoran.
Who was there?
Siapa saja ada di sana?
The guy with the dog. He broke a plate. Remember?
Orang yang bawa anjing itu. Dia memecahkan piring. Ingat?
He was at the fair by the bouncy castle.
Dia di pameran di dekat istana balon.
So we're looking for a dog now?
Jadi, sekarang kita mencari anjing?
Who organized the fair?
Siapa penyelenggara festival?
Do you like the book?
Kau suka bukunya?
I'll come next week.
Aku datang minggu depan.
Take care, Basiu.
Sampai jumpa, Basiu.
Here, son.
Ini, Nak.
Eat, honey.
Makanlah, Sayang.
Go on, eat.
Ayo, makan.
One to me!
Satu orang ke sini!
Clear!
Aman!
Guys, where's the boy?
Di mana anak itu?
Clear.
Kosong.
-What the fuck? -There's no one here.
Kosong apa maksudnya?
The basement's over there.
Basemennya di sana.
Fucking hell!
Keparat!
-Was the door locked? -Open.
- Tadi pintunya terkunci? - Terbuka.
Stop!
Berhenti!
Police! Get down!
Polisi! Tiarap!
Piotruś!
Piotruś!
Okay. Leave her.
Biarkan dia.
-Piotruś! -Mom!
- Piotruś! - Ibu!
Mom.
Ibu.
Are you okay?
Kau tidak apa-apa?
Yes.
Ya.
You comfortable, fucker?
Nyaman, Bajingan?
I asked if you're comfortable, you fuck.
Kutanya apa kau nyaman, Bajingan?
Nicki testified that Adam Poznański's death was an accident.
Nicki bersaksi bahwa kematian Adam Poznański tidak disengaja.
Chief Adamczyk was supposed to cover it up,
Pak Adamczyk seharusnya menutupinya
and Nicki was supposed to hide the body.
dan Nicki seharusnya menyembunyikan mayatnya.
Nicki is the son
Nicki ini putra…
of the girl in the photo?
gadis di foto itu?
And Chojnacki's.
Dan Chojnacki.
The girl gave birth at the age of 14.
Gadis itu melahirkan pada usia 14 tahun.
She received psychiatric treatment.
Setelah itu dia dirawat psikiater.
At the age of 18, she took her own life, in front of her son.
Pada usia 18 tahun, dia bunuh diri.
It's not known when his psychosis started,
Tidak diketahui kapan psikosisnya dimulai,
but it developed slowly.
tapi berkembang perlahan.
That's why Piotr Sarman is still alive.
Itu sebabnya Piotr Sarman masih hidup.
He was his first victim.
Harusnya dia korban pertamanya.
Nicki wasn't abused by Chojnacki?
Nicki tidak dilecehkan Chojnacki?
He didn't say that.
Dia tidak bilang.
But he doesn't talk much.
Tapi dia tidak banyak bicara.
-Chojnacki took care of him somehow. -Took care of him?
Chojnacki merawatnya.
In some twisted way, yes.
Dengan cara yang aneh, ya.
Okay, we'll charge…
Baik, kita akan menuntut…
Chief Adamczyk, and also the young Chojnacki and Filipiak.
Pak Adamczyk, juga Chojnacki dan Filipiak muda.
It'll be hard to convict Chojnacki and Filipiak.
Sulit membuktikan Chojnacki dan Filipiak bersalah.
The court will decide.
Pengadilan yang akan memutuskan.
I can't forgive myself that the same thing happened to Michał.
Aku tidak bisa memaafkan diriku karena Michał juga mengalami itu.
I've been thinking about the missing case files for Adam Poznański.
Saya memikirkan berkas kasus Adam Poznański yang hilang.
We need to search the chief's house,
Kita harus menggeledah rumah Kapolda,
but I'm afraid he's gotten rid of them by now.
tapi mungkin sudah dia singkirkan sekarang.
I thought so too.
Saya kira begitu.
Then I remembered that in some prosecutor's offices,
Lalu saya ingat, di beberapa kantor kejaksaan,
they hide files in the noncriminal registry
berkas disembunyikan di arsip perkara nonpidana
to improve statistics.
demi memperbaiki statistik.
But not here.
Tapi di sini tidak.
I checked our registry, and
Saya memeriksa arsip kita dan…
the case files were there all along.
ternyata berkas kasusnya selama ini ada di sana.
You're suggesting someone from our office hid them?
Maksudmu ada orang kantor menyembunyikannya?
Yes.
Ya.
Who?
Siapa?
You.
Bapak.
You're joking.
Kau bercanda.
Adamczyk decided to cooperate.
Adamczyk memutuskan bekerja sama.
He testified that you helped cover for Chojnacki.
Dia bersaksi Bapak membantu menutupi Chojnacki.
He's lying.
Dia bohong.
I don't think so.
Saya rasa tidak.
You protected the man who hurt your son.
Bapak melindungi orang yang menyakiti putra Bapak.
I wasn't protecting Chojnacki.
Aku tidak melindungi Chojnacki.
I didn't know he hurt my son.
Aku tidak tahu dia menyakiti putraku.
The court will decide.
Pengadilan yang akan memutuskan.
BASED ON THE NOVEL COLORS OF EVIL: BLACK BY MAŁGORZATA OLIWIA SOBCZAK
BERDASARKAN NOVEL "COLORS OF EVIL: BLACK" KARYA MAŁGORZATA OLIWIA SOBCZAK
Subtitle translation by: Katarzyna Błachnio-Sitkiewicz
Terjemahan subtitle oleh June Arya